<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>putz.space - Lessons Learned</title><link href="https://web.putz.space/" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://web.putz.space/feeds/lessons-learned.atom.xml" rel="self"/><id>https://web.putz.space/</id><updated>2023-06-08T12:41:34-05:00</updated><subtitle>Web Designer, Developer and Freelancer</subtitle><entry><title>What I learned from putz.space</title><link href="https://web.putz.space/lessons-learned/lessons-learned/" rel="alternate"/><published>2023-06-08T12:41:34-05:00</published><updated>2023-06-08T12:41:34-05:00</updated><author><name>Pierce Putz</name></author><id>tag:web.putz.space,2023-06-08:/lessons-learned/lessons-learned/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Reflecting on lessons learned from this portfolio project.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Lessons learned&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the course of creating this web portfolio I've learned the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Web Design&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don't forget to make live content. Important for testing design.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Design systems are iterative, they start messy and can be analyzed for better definition over time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How to draw focus:&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use of borders on controls, titles and grounding info (i.e: where am I?).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use of typography and color to group/define content.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Learned more details about how &lt;a href="https://getpelican.com"&gt;Pelican&lt;/a&gt; templating and other internals works.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Project management&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Time management is essential.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Problem solving is an inevitable time cost you'll pay. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Solving issues in one project can lead to solutions in another.&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pagination design work made updating Ludo Air's easier.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Understanding project purpose is key in knowing what to prioritize.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When to cut material and save it for implementation later.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Misc&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I guess I'm really into loons lol.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Lessons Learned"/><category term="Web Design"/></entry><entry><title>Purpose driven design</title><link href="https://web.putz.space/lessons-learned/purpose-first/" rel="alternate"/><published>2023-06-08T12:28:59-05:00</published><updated>2023-06-08T12:28:59-05:00</updated><author><name>Pierce Putz</name></author><id>tag:web.putz.space,2023-06-08:/lessons-learned/purpose-first/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Diving into the importance of good Information Architecture &amp;amp; direction.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The first step to making a website is to ask a lot of questions.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall, you need to understand the following before even touching code:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What are the &lt;strong&gt;goals&lt;/strong&gt; of this website?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Who are the &lt;strong&gt;users&lt;/strong&gt; and what are their needs?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How will you create &lt;strong&gt;content&lt;/strong&gt;?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is the operating &lt;strong&gt;context&lt;/strong&gt;?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Information Architecture is a blueprint&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main purpose of &lt;strong&gt;Information Architecture&lt;/strong&gt; is making information findable and understandable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I start a new project, I begin my research with &lt;strong&gt;Content, Context and Users&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Context&lt;/strong&gt; — &lt;em&gt;Why? Where?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Background Research&lt;/em&gt; — goals, plans, schedule &amp;amp; budget. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Meetings&lt;/em&gt; — understand the current operations &amp;amp; organization of who I'm working with. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Technology Assessment&lt;/em&gt; — decide on/learn hosting platform, set up dev tools, perform gap analysis.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Content&lt;/strong&gt; — &lt;em&gt;What? How?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Heuristic Evaluation&lt;/em&gt; — assess design accessibility and design choices.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Content Analysis and Mapping&lt;/em&gt; — gather docs and media to investigate, map relationships.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Benchmarking&lt;/em&gt; — assess how well the website performs &amp;amp; compare to similar ones. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Users&lt;/strong&gt; — &lt;em&gt;Who?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Analytics&lt;/em&gt; — see metrics about website usage.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Personas &amp;amp; Use Cases&lt;/em&gt; — investigate audience, user flows and needs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;User Interviews &amp;amp; Testing&lt;/em&gt; — conduct usability tests and understand user needs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;From Nothing to Something&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The goal of collecting the information above is to shine a light that lets you see the &lt;em&gt;overall&lt;/em&gt; situation. Questions that weren't clear before start to make sense as more knowledge is gathered and ideas start to take shape.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eventually it becomes possible to craft a &lt;strong&gt;strategy&lt;/strong&gt;. These are the lessons learned and an attempt to organize information into an actionable plan that others can understand. Once a plan is ready, it's time to present it to anyone who will be working on the website so that everyone is on the same page. This requires meetings and collaboration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The strategy guides &lt;strong&gt;design&lt;/strong&gt; planning and creating what will become the actual website. These are the first drafts and documents that will guide actually creating the website prototypes according to a vision.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Afterwards &lt;strong&gt;implementation&lt;/strong&gt; is possible based on all the work that was done to plan the new website or redesign. It is important to document how the website works for &lt;strong&gt;administration&lt;/strong&gt;. i.e; maintenance and future developments so that the website still meets its goals as it grows.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The real process of architecting a website is &lt;em&gt;less linear&lt;/em&gt; than what I've presented, but this is the general course I try to follow since it is the most effective. &lt;strong&gt;It all starts with understanding goals and mapping things out though.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My experience has been much better when I take the time to research the full project scope before I set off creating any ideas. Getting the order right helps sort out questions &lt;em&gt;in advance&lt;/em&gt; instead of getting stuck with no direction, or focusing on superficial issues and missing the deeper structural ones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Plus it makes project maintenance soooo much easier when there's a plan with an actual vision, instead of a hodgepodge mess of ideas that come and go.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Lessons Learned"/><category term="Web Design"/></entry><entry><title>Self-taught Web Design</title><link href="https://web.putz.space/lessons-learned/self-teaching/" rel="alternate"/><published>2023-06-08T12:19:09-05:00</published><updated>2023-06-08T12:19:09-05:00</updated><author><name>Pierce Putz</name></author><id>tag:web.putz.space,2023-06-08:/lessons-learned/self-teaching/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Insights from my own journey in self-taught web design.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I decided this spring that I want to become a &lt;strong&gt;Full Stack Developer&lt;/strong&gt;. I looked around at coding bootcamps, but I felt that for my own schedule &amp;amp; commitments that teaching myself would be most effective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, I decided to come up with my own path and &lt;em&gt;here's how!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Table of Contents&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#goals"&gt;Start with Goals&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#path-to-full-stack"&gt;Path to Full Stack Development&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#sticking-with-it"&gt;Sticking with it&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name="goals"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Start with Goals&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first step on this journey was to &lt;strong&gt;identify my goals&lt;/strong&gt;. The focus on goals &lt;strong&gt;helps when important questions come up&lt;/strong&gt;, which there are a lot of when you're on your own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Personally, I've been interested in work from home jobs and flexible scheduling. I also like working on creative projects. A lot of this was already work I have been doing as a hobby, so I'm well situated to dive in deeper. Plus it'll make my already existing sites more sharp.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Long story short,&lt;/em&gt; I landed on web development as a good investment of my time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name="path-to-full-stack"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Path to Full Stack Development&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The process&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first step to actually making this all &lt;em&gt;happen&lt;/em&gt; was to figure out the process from beginning to end.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It went something like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Research and compile a typical curriculum for &lt;strong&gt;Full Stack Development&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Find suitable books to read.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Decide on which &lt;strong&gt;portfolio projects&lt;/strong&gt; to make.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Keep focused and follow the timeframe.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My goal is to be done in roughly 6 months to a year from when I started in March.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The timeframe for completing this is flexible since there's no way to really know how long it will take initially, but as I go it's easier to get a sense of how long I'll need to read books, work on projects, etc. Keeping an time log of hours spent on portfolio projects also helps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Curriculum&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the curriculum iteslf, I landed on these units as the &lt;em&gt;important&lt;/em&gt; areas to cover:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#reading-fundamentals"&gt;Fundamentals &amp;amp; Foundation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#reading-web-design"&gt;Web Design&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#reading-javascript"&gt;Frameworks and Libraries&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#reading-backend"&gt;Databases and Backend&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#reading-security-deployment-operations"&gt;Security, Deployment and Operations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#reading-workflow"&gt;Workflow and Nailing the Interview&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Coming up with &lt;strong&gt;portfolio projects&lt;/strong&gt; has been just a matter of looking at what areas of my own life have related needs that web design skills can actually solve. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My first project since starting, &lt;a href="https://air.ludoloon.studio"&gt;Ludo Air&lt;/a&gt;, is a combination of my love of flight sim and my already existing online studio, &lt;a href="https://ludoloon.studio"&gt;LudoLoon Studio&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This website of course serves as portfolio to show off my web progress. My next project I'm thinking of is a Social Media Dashboard since I'm sick of dealing with Instagram and Twitter directly lol.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Reading List&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's a list of some books that I've either been reading, or will get around to reading by the end of my studies. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most helpful ones (to me personally) are in bold. Some of these I had read previous to officially starting this project, but I went back and reviewed them to take notes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;NOTE: This evolves as I get through the books and sort which ones are actually useful or not.&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;a name="reading-fundamentals"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Fundamentals&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Learning Web Design - A Beginner's Guide to HTML, CSS, JavaScript, and Web Graphics (2018, O'Reilly Media)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://git-scm.com/book/en/v2/Git-Basics-Getting-a-Git-Repository"&gt;Git Basics&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a name="reading-web-design"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Web Design&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A Web for Everyone (2014, Rosenfeld Media)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Design Systems - A practical guide to creating design languages for digital products (2017, Smashing Media).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://git-scm.com/book/en/v2/Distributed-Git-Distributed-Workflows"&gt;Distributed Git&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don't Make Me Think (3rd ed.) (Voices that Matter)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Information Architecture - For the Web and Beyond (O'Reilly Media, Inc.)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Principles of Beautiful Web Design (2020, SitePoint)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rocket Surgery Made Easy (Voices that Matter)
&lt;a name="reading-javascript"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Javascript Frameworks and Libraries&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;JavaScript - The Definitive Guide - Master the World's Most-Used Programming Language (2020, O'Reilly Media)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;JavaScript Everywhere: Building Cross-Platform Applications with GraphQL, React, React Native, and Electron (2020, O’Reilly Media) &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Learning React Modern Patterns for Developing React Apps (2020, O'Reilly)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mastering React Test-Driven Development (2022, Packt Publishing)
&lt;a name="reading-backend"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Databases and Backend&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Full Stack Web Development Guide - Everything Node JS, Express, APIs, EJS, React JS, Database Fundamentals, SQL Databases (2022, Independently published)
&lt;a name="reading-security-deployment-operations"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Security, Deployment and Operations&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The DevOps Handbook - How to Create World-Class Agility, Reliability, &amp;amp; Security in Technology Organizations (2021, IT Revolution Press)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Web Security for Developers (2020, Random House LCC)
&lt;a name="reading-workflow"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Workflow &amp;amp; Nailing the Interview&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Design Is a Job (2022, A Book Apart)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cracking the Coding Interview (2015, CareerCup)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Art of Agile Development (2021, O'Reilly Media)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name="sticking-with-it"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Sticking with it&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you can imagine, the easy part is coming up with the roadmap. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to get through the curriculum it's important to have a &lt;strong&gt;schedule&lt;/strong&gt;. I've been &lt;strong&gt;setting deadlines&lt;/strong&gt; to make sure that I don't get stuck on one project and risk the whole effort getting sidetracked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Writing everything down is crucial&lt;/strong&gt;. I use &lt;a href="https://zim-wiki.org"&gt;Zim Wiki&lt;/a&gt; which makes it easy to connect documents, but any good notetaking app will do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Spreadsheets&lt;/em&gt; for hours worked on projects.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Tasklists&lt;/em&gt; for next steps.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Notes&lt;/em&gt; of what you've read or planning projects.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Calendar reminders&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;keeping tasklists&lt;/strong&gt; for when I have a moment to work remind me what steps I'm on currently or what I need to be reading.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Staying well&lt;/strong&gt; is crucial, which means taking breaks when burnt out and scheduling time to take care of yourself as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Assessing study progress&lt;/strong&gt; is an important process as milestones are acheived. This means deciding on next steps like what book to read next, framework to learn, or portfolio project to do.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Lessons Learned"/><category term="Web Design"/></entry></feed>